<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse vppon a question of the estate of this time. Faithfully translated out of French by E.A.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854191</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20505)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 421:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse vppon a question of the estate of this time. Faithfully translated out of French by E.A.</title>
                  <author>Aggas, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shop ouer against the great South doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.A. = Edward Aggas.</note>
                  <note>A2r has caption: A question of this time. Why doth not the King become a Catholike?.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A question of this time.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Diſcourſe</hi> Vppon a Queſtion of the Eſtate of this time.</p>
            <p>Faithfully translated out of French by E. A.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> Iohn Wolfe, <hi>and are to be ſolde at his ſhop ouer againſt the great South doore of Paules.</hi> 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19600:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19600:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A queſtion of this time.</hi> Why doth not the King become a Catholike? If he would become a Catholike, his realme would ſoone be at peace: all his ſubiectes would obey him, and without any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie acknowledge him.</head>
            <head type="sub">This is the daily ſpeeche of diuers: but let vs conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not of perſons as farre different in humours, as they differ in intents.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the leaguers began to doubt of the good ſucceſſe of their affaires, to miſtruſt their owne forces, and to imagine, that in the and, the King might become maiſter, they gaue out, that it was requiſite he ſhould become a Catholike, alleadging, that afterwarde on ſuch aſſuraunce as they might gather, that he meant good earneſt, they would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be their King, ſuppoſing, that if they muſt néedes grow to that paſſe, that of neceſſitie they muſt obey him, they would at the leaſt perſwade and make the ſimple people (whome they had abuſed) to beléeue that their firſt ſtirring vp of theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and troubles of war, tended only to the preſeruation of the Cathol. Apoſtol. Romiſh religion, and the Kings conuerſion. But theſe ſpéeches would much better haue beſéemed the mouths of other Catholikes that did continue in their dueties, then theirs: for they are for to remember, that the late deceaſed King was as great a catholike as any of his predeceſſours, and yet was it hée whome the Leaguers did firſt ſet vpon, againſt him directed they their firſt exclamations, iniuries, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in his life time began they their conſpiracies, rebellions, and diſobedience: againſt his perſon and eſtate did they ſo farre
<pb facs="tcp:19600:3"/>attempt, as with the aduiſe of the moſt apparant profeſſours of Romiſh religion among them, to deliberate, conſult of, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his death, whom finally moſt barbarouſly and horribly they ſtroke and ſlew through a Iacobine Friar, who was by them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and brought thereto.</p>
            <p>The ſame Leaguers are alſo to remember, that by their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and diffamatory Libelles printed and publiſhed at ſuch time as they thought the K. that now is to be ouerthrown &amp; paſt hope of euer attaining to the ſucceſſion of this Crown, they proclaimd him a relaps, aduowing, that albeit he woulde returne into the boſome of the catholike Church, yet he was no longer receiuable to the ſucceſſion of the Crowne, and ſo conſequently his ſubiectes were diſpenſed with for acknowledging him or yéelding him anie obedience: yea this they cauſed to be preached abroad by the hired tongues of their preachers. Many other ſuch ſpéeches and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the ſame Authors coulde I here alleadge to reprooue and conuince them of contradiction, and ſo to ſhew them to be nothing leſſe then ledde with ſo holy a deſire of the kings conuerſion, were it the Argument of this Diſcourſe: but being content with this litle, which in reſpect of them, I haue but touched by the way, I will indeuour to anſwere and ſatiſfie others that doe vſe the ſame ſpéech, albeit with other affection and meaning then they.</p>
            <p>Among ſundry that giue themſelues out to be the Kings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, we daily heare no other ſpéeches but theſe: Would to God the King would become a Catholike: That he would vouchſafe ſo much content to the Catholikes, as to go to maſſe: ſo ſhoulde the Leaguers no longer haue any cloke for their rebellion, the Townes that they holde ſhould yéelde him obedience: and to be briefe, we ſhould obtaine peace, that is ſo neceſſary to this realme.</p>
            <p>My maiſters, ſith you are the Kings ſeruants, or at the leaſt, that you do ſo terme your ſelues, and that it ſéemes, beſides your own ſayings, that you would haue vs beléeue you ſo to be: I dare preſume that you will hearken to my reaſons, and accept of them with a milde and vpright mind: for how frée ſoeuer I be in my words, yet do I meane to ſay nothing that may be offenſiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
            <p>I pray you, my maiſters, theſe wiſhes and deſires, together
<pb facs="tcp:19600:3"/>with ſuch zealous ſighs as ſéeme to procéede from your ſtomaks, do they ſimply growe of a holy affection to the wealth and peace of Gods Church and this realme, and the ſaluation of the King, or rather of ſome affected ſhew, then of any true eſſence of good will? I am content to take them in the firſt ſenſe, which is the beſt, and to beléeue that ſincerely you are of opinion, that if the King would ſpéedely, without tarrying vntill a Councell hath determined the controuerſies that at this day raigne through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out chriſtendome about the diuerſities of opinions, concerning the Cath. Apoſt. and Romiſh religion, yéelde himſelfe to bée in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Catholike religion, his realme would inmediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grow to peace, and all factions and partialities amongeſt vs ceaſe.</p>
            <p>I would to God that that were the onely let, and in ſo holy a deſire wil I neuer giue place to any. Beſides, I am aſſured, that the King is ſo ready to learne, that he will eaſely be content to be inſtructed and brought to the Cath. Apoſt. Romiſh religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in caſe any man can ſhew and prooue him to be in any error: yet, may I tell you, that this remedy is not ſufficient to cure our diſeaſes. Do you beléeue, that the Leaguers doe in heart deſire that the King would be brought to the Cath. Apoſt. Romiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? If you do ſo thinke, you are deceiued. They ſée me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, but they would be very ſory it ſhould be ſo, yea, albeit the King had done it, yet would they yéelde him no more obedience then they now do, but rather they woulde vſe his returne to the Cath. Church as a meane to ſeuer the Germans, Switzers, and other proteſtant nations from the Kings friendſhip, and ſo bring him to looſe al credit and reputation both within and without the realme: a matter which great princes do continue according as they are thought of, and are in effect conſtant, couragious and ſtedfaſt in their good purpoſes. Marke therefore this one onely matter among many other of like pollicy, which now I thinke méete to ſhew you, for ſo may you diſcouer the trueth of theſe their ſpéeches.</p>
            <p>The chiefe of the League, and among others the D. of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, perceiuing one of the kings chiefeſt humane forces to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the ſuccour that he expecteth from the Germaines, fearing
<pb facs="tcp:19600:4"/>nothing ſo much as the diſcent of an army of that nation, haue by their agents and factors giuen to vnderſtand to the princes Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and other lords and potentates of Germany, that the King was become, or at the leaſt had ſworne and promiſed the officers of the crowne and French nobility, that he would become a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike: That already both about his perſon, and in his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and moſt important affaires within the realme and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, he vſed almoſt none but Catholikes. Which to be ſo, ſayde they, mark what they be whom he hath ſent to be dealers in the leauy of ſuch Souldiours as he deſireth of you: be they not all Catholikes? Yea, euen the ſame Miniſters and Ambaſſadours whome the late King vſed? What occaſion therefore haue your Lordſhips to grant your ſuccor to the king of Nauarre (for they do not otherwiſe entitle the King) rather then vnto the houſe of Lorraine and Guiſe, or to the King of Spaine their king and confederate? With this ſleight and ſubtilty haue they troubled the Kings affaires in Germany, and ſlacked the leauy of his men of war. What then would they do if indéede the king were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Catholike, conſidering that vpon a ſimple apparance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they haue ſo ſhaken the amity which the princes of Germany do beare to the king? Hereupon therefore ye may conclude, that al the inſtance that the leaguers make, to cauſe the K. to returne to the Catholike religion, tends only to withdraw from him the loue of forren proteſtant Princes, ſo to weaken his forces of ſo much. Alſo that albeit he were become a Cath. yet the King of Spaine, with the houſes of Lorraine and Guiſe, and other his ennemies, would neuertheleſſe proſecute the warre againſt him, and that with more power and ſtrength then yet they haue: for vndoubtedly they would vſe the power of Germany &amp; other the proteſtants that now do aſſiſt the king in the defence of his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſine and lawfull right to this crowne, which they indeuour to wreſt from him, and al other the princes of his blood and familie.</p>
            <p>This is the cauſe that the King (being well informed of the drifts and practiſes aforeſaide, hath diſpatched the L. Vicount of Turenne to the Quéene of England, and thence into Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to aſſure the proteſtant Princes of the contrarie of that that his enemies haue bruited among them to his hindrance, and to
<pb facs="tcp:19600:4"/>ſhew them that it was no newes that he vſed the ſeruice of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks, conſidering he had the like before he came to this crown. Alſo, that he intended equally to fauour and vſe all his obedient ſeruants and ſubiects without acception or difference of religion: with aſſurance likewiſe to the ſaide Lady the Quéene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and proteſtant princes of Germany, that at what time ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſhal cauſe himſelfe to be inſtructed in the catholike religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he will withall procure to al chriſtendome the benefite of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union in one ſole faith and religion, thereby at once to ceaſe all diuiſions, warres and partialities ariſing vpon the diuerſitie of opinions in religion. Let vs therefore, I pray you, a little exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what may bring to all chriſtendome in generall, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to this realme, the accompliſhment of your deſires.</p>
            <p>It were ſomewhat if the king were inſtructed and brought to the cath. Apoſt. and Romiſh religion, and with all my heart my ſelfe do wiſh it as earneſtly as any of you, yet muſt you with me confeſſe, that albeit we might reap the contentment of the fight hereof, yet his ſubiectes that are indued with the like opinion, would not neuertheleſſe be ſo ſoone reclaimed: witnes Caſſiodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus who in the perſon of Theodorike king of the Gothes dooth ſay: <hi>Religion dependeth not vpon our commaundement, for no man is forced to beleeue againſt his will:</hi> witnes alſo S. Bernard, who in another place ſaith: <hi>Faith muſt be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not forced,</hi> whereby theſe two great perſonages doe frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, that kings haue no power ouer the conſciences: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, nothing ſhould be ſo voluntary as religion, wherein, if the ſpirit be forced, it may wel be ſaid, that religion is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and there is none at all left. And indéed we haue found that our kings how zealous catholikes ſoeuer, could not in thréeſcore yeares ſpace neither by their examples of earneſt Catho. Apoſt. and Romiſh religion, neyther by fires, tortures or temporall weapons tame or force the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of their ſubiects. To what purpoſe then were it for the king to be a catholike, vnleſſe his proteſtant ſubiects would ſo become alſo? I do already ſéeme to heare ſome cry out ſaying: we would perſwade, yea, euen force the king to denounce war againſt them, vnleſſe they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues. Alas, ſo ſhould yereturne into that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:19600:5"/>out ye ſéeke to depart. You ſay, The king becomming a catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, we ſhal be at peace: yet in your other diſcourſe you ſée, that créeping out of one war, we ſhall fall into another as dangerous, or rather worſe then the former. Let vs then crie alarum as much as we liſt, for that is no cure for our calamities: weapons prouoke weapons, and our minds only are ſicke, which we muſt ſéeke to cure by documents and reaſons onely. Thus much for the particularity of this realme.</p>
            <p>Shall the generall ſtate of chriſtendome be any whit the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Is the king more able to reduce forren proteſtant Nations to the cath. apoſt. Romiſh religion? There wil be no want of firebrands of war to tel me with their vſuall diſcourſes: That the king who is a great warriour, may with the aſſiſtance of the coyne and forces of our holy father the Pope, and the King of Spaine, in fewe yeares reduce the forraine people and Nations into the boſome of the Romiſh church. Such diſcourſes are much amiſſe, as experience of that which is paſt teacheth vs: for ſo ſhould we reenter into ſuch a laborinth, as without other more milde and lawfull meanes, and Gods great helpe, we ſhall not eaſely get out againe: yea, ſo ſhould we fall to turning of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite whéele, able to leade vs and all chriſtendome to a finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, ye are to thinke, that it were very vnſéemely to the inuiolable faith of the king, to his conſtancie, inuincible magnanimitie, honour and reputation, ſo ſleightly and ſodaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to alter his religion, whether in hope of a more peaceable raigne, or in intent to force and racke conſciences, and in all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie to leauy war againſt thoſe that haue aſſiſted him in all his aduerſities, and againſt whome we are to imagine, that he beareth no bad minde, ſith himſelfe being in the like caſe hath felt, that euen in his ſoule, he thought it good. Which alſo is the cauſe, that he iudging others affection to religion by his owne, will not force the couſciences of vs catholikes, and woulde you then that he ſhould force the proteſtants? Iudge ye whether it were any reaſon. Do we meane to play with the K. and make him in his actions (which ought to be kept in meaſure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe) walke after our fantaſies? Let vs at this time be content
<pb facs="tcp:19600:5"/>with his declarations publiſhed both before &amp; ſince his comming to this crowne, which haue relation hereto, and doe open to vs his reſolution.</p>
            <p>I haue peraduenture more briefly then I ſhoulde, or then the matter deſerues, touched ſuch inconueniences as are to be feared, or may come to paſſe, in caſe the king ſhould reclaime himſelfe to the cathol. religion as readily as ſome doe deſire: but becauſe by this little that I haue ſaid, others may eaſily ſupply ſuch conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as may be conteined in this behalfe, which I leaue to the diſcretion of thoſe that liſt more déepely to penetrate thereinto, I wil procéede to intreat of the profit and commoditie that may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to al chriſtendome, ſo long as the king ſtandeth faſt in the declarations which he hath publiſhed both before and ſince his comming to the crowne, for matter of conſcience and religion, wherein he alwayes ſubmitted him ſelfe to the determination of a generall or nationall councell.</p>
            <p>The king is not alone in this realme of his religion, there are but ouer many inſtructed therein, that do profeſſe the ſame. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this realme alone are there many withdrawen from the Romiſh Church, but alſo in England, Scotland, Denmarke, Sweden Poleland, Germany, Switzerland, and other places, being more then halfe chriſtendome. What way therfore do ye thinke to be beſt to reclaime al theſe nations to the obedience of the cath. apoſt. Romiſh church, whether war, or a frée generall councell? Inquiſitions, fires, gibbets, murders, warres, battels, fiege of townes, leagues, conuenticles, ſlaughters, aſſaults, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings: in briefe, all other meanes and ſubtilities in the worlde, that theſe <hi>30.</hi> yeres could be practiſed to the great deſolation and detriment of al chriſtendome, but eſpecially of this realme, haue as yet nothing preuailed. Only they haue made a number of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, Libertines and Epicures, contemners of God, his word, and church: we haue found theſe medicines to be no fitter to the cure of the ſickenes of the mind, then is a ſtrong, cleane, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming wine to the frantike or burning ague: but rather to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oile to quench a flaming fire: or as when a man hath paine in his arme, for the curing therof to cut off his leg, or other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. My maiſters, the Apoſtles and antient fathers of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:19600:6"/>neuer vſed any ſuch tooles for the rooting out of thoſe errours and hereſies which from time to time were ſowen and planted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Marke in the Acts of the Apoſtles what they did in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in the cutting off of meats, and aboliſhing of Iudaiſme which ſome through the circumciſion went about to continue in the church, after grace giuen by Ieſus Chriſt. Conſider what the Emperour Conſtantine the great did for the ſuppreſſion and condemning of the hereſie of Arrius. Sée alſo what other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours did in like caſes, what courſe thy tooke to aboliſh the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of the Neſtorians, Pelagians, Anabaptiſts, and others, as the Counſelles called for the ſame do teſtifie. Why then ſhall not we do the like in theſe dayes, where the queſtion concerneth not a handfull of people retired from the Romiſh church, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen halfe chriſtendome?</p>
            <p>But now here commeth ſome angrie fellow that will tell me, that the hereſies of theſe dayes are already condemned by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent: and therfore, if that a proceſſe alredy iudged euen by decrée, where all parties haue anſwered reciprocally, is not to be reduced to the file, what ſhal then become of a proceſſe iudged by default, and contumacie, where the parties haue neither appeared nor anſwered? But omitting al other cauſes of nullitie aleadged againſt the ſaid Councell, as by ſundry bookes expreſſely written doth appeare: the Proteſtants and Huguenots do ſay and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that they are not heard in the ſaid councel of Trent. That albeit they were thereto ſummoned and called, yet they durſt not appeare, as doubting of the ſafety of their perſons, by reaſon of a certaine principle both then, and yet holden by ſome of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, importing, <hi>That faith is not to be kept with heretikes:</hi> and fearing the like ſucceſſe as happened to thoſe, who contrarie to the publike faith, and the Emperour Signiſmundes ſafeconduct, were put to death at the councel of Conſtance. If we were once ſufficiently grounded to condemne this opinion and errour, may we not be ſo againe? It is not the firſt time that there haue béene diuers councels holden for the rooting out of one ſelfe hereſie. Sith there haue béene two Councels holden in Italie, and one Sinode in France, for the determining of the opinion of a meane Deacon of Saint Maurice of Angiers, is it not greater reaſon to call a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb facs="tcp:19600:6"/>frée councell for ſo many peoples and nations of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as at this day are of diuers opinions? Let vs then ſhewe that we feare not the touchſtone: yea, let them know that equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and trueth are on our ſide, which can neuer be reuerſed in the preſence of God, who by his holy ſpirite alwaies aſſiſteth a frée councel lawfully aſſembled and holden.</p>
            <p>I could be content here to make a digreſſion and exclamation againſt our holy fathers the Popes, who are or ſhould be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fathers of all faithfull and Catholike people, for ſuffering ſo much chriſtian bloud to be ſhead about theſe arguments and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies in religion: alſo, for that they haue rather fauoured, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and conſented to the leuying of ſuch wars hereabout, then vſed the ſpirituall ſword, the which is Gods word, for the cutting off of the courſe of hereſie: but in reſpect of the reuerence of their memorie: the place that they haue holden, the honor that I owe to that holy ſea, and eſchewing of offence, I will holde my peace.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, that as this ſickenes of diuerſitie of opinions in religion is ſpirituall, ſo it is requiſite thereto to applie ſpiritual remedies and medicines. To ſay with ſome, that the king is to be inſtructed, we may ſay as much of al other that holde the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions as he doth, and ſo when ſhal we haue done teaching of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one particularly? Againe, thinke you ſo to win the conſent of the inhabitants of England, Scotland, Denmarke, Sweden, Germany, and other countries that haue frée exerciſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion without controlement? Wéene you that the doctours of Sorbonne, and other ſuch diuines ſhall be welcome to them in particular, when they come to miniſter vnto them this foode and inſtruction? Ye are deceiued: it is a méere mockerie, neither can that be the neceſſarie remedy to this diſeaſe. Nothing but a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councell can cure ſo generall a ſickeneſſe. For the honour of God therfore, my Maiſters, you that are ſeruauntes to God and the king, as well Cleargie men as others, neuer withſtand this courſe. And you of the League, let reaſon rule you, as well your affaires are but in bad caſe: I ſay and affirme, that vnto ſuch as in lieu of employing themſelues about the calling of a generall councel, ſhall withſtand and hinder the ſame, we may iuſtly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the cauſes of whatſoeuer domage may enſue to the catho.
<pb facs="tcp:19600:7"/>apoſtol. and Romiſh religion, aduowing that they be guilty and anſwerable before god for al the robberies, murders, fires, ſpoils, ranſoms, violations, ruines, calamities, and other outrages, and exceſſe of the warres. I know well enough, my maiſters, that many of you do wiſh that the king would become a catholike, to the end ye might haue peace, and ye deſire peace to the end to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to your houſes, there to inioy your woonted commodities and pleaſures. But if ye obtaine not this wiſh at Gods hand, ye may be well aſſured, that (as in a certaine place it is ſaide) it is becauſe ye aſke amiſſe. God knoweth your hearts, and can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you as Chriſt anſwered the ſonnes of Zebede, <hi>Ye wot not what ye aske:</hi> Let vs firſt therefore aſke and ſéeke after the kingdome of God and his righteouſnes, ſo ſhall all things be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereto. For I do certainely beléeue that the firſt point re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit hereto, were to change and reforme our maners, our pride, vanitie, couetouſnes, ambition and pleaſures, with other our ſins and bad demeanors, and to embrace charitie with the loue of God and our neighbor, which at this day are not onely cooled, but euen almoſt quite quenched in vs. But ſith I am no diuine, without grounding my ſelfe any déeper vpon diuinity, I will ende this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the ſame ſimple ſtile wherein I began.</p>
            <p>A hundred and a hundred times, conſidering the ſpoiles and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations procéeding of the tragedies ſtirred vp throughout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, but eſpecially in this realme, vnder the pretence of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of opinions in matter of religion, I haue ſtudied how they might be appeaſed, yet ſtill my minde hath giuen me, and I haue thought it good (vnder Gods good pleaſure, who only is able to frée vs from theſe miſeries) for ſome mighty chriſtian prince, touched with the ſpirite of God, a louer of his owne ſaluation, together with the peace and vnion of the vniuerſall Church, whoſe worde and faith had neuer bene called in queſtion, to labour to the pope, emperour, and other chriſtian kings and princes, to ſummon an aſſembly in maner of a councell, or generall conference, whereto it might be lawfull for al chriſtian nations to ſend their embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, deputies, doctours and diuines, men of milde and tractable humours, ſuch as eſpecially reſpected the glory of God, the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of themſelues and their neighbours, and the peace of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome,
<pb facs="tcp:19600:7"/>to the ende, by the teſtimony and authority of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, the auncient councels, the doctours and fathers of the church, ſuch as haue alwayes béene receiued and allowed, to agrée and conclude vpon a publike and general confeſſion of faith, that may touch whatſoeuer is in controuerſie, or diuerſly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted concerning the catholike apoſtolike and Romiſh doctrine and religion, as alſo that euery the ſaide embaſſadours and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties ſhould be authorized with epſeciall power and proxie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to grant, promiſe and ſweare in the behalfe of thoſe that might haue choſen, and ſent them, to obſerue and kéepe, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly and inuiolably to cauſe to be obſerued and kept, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall be decided, concluded and decréed in the ſaide aſſembly. And withal reuoluing in my mind who were the fitteſt prince in chriſtendome, whom god might vſe as an inſtrument in ſo great a worke, my heart gaue me aboue <hi>8.</hi> yeares ſince, that the king now raigning temporally ouer vs, was moſt méete: yea, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince haue I bin perſuaded, that god ſtil preſerued him to that end. In which perſuaſion I am greatly confirmed, when priuatly I call to mind Gods wonderfull works, in the calling and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to this crown. For it hath bin maruellous yea, I would gladly ſay euen miraculous, had not euery one ſéene it, or had not many particularities béene noted in ſundry former writings: either if I wiſt, that among the kings ſeruants (for to them ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially do I direct my ſpéech) there were any yet ſo dull, as not to haue conſidered, and diuers times meditated vpon the courſe of things paſſed, I could gladly ſtay vppon a briefe rehearſall of the ſame in this place: but ſtudying for brenitie, leaſt I ſhould be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I will onely ſay thus much: that ſith ſo extraordinarily, contrary to the opinion and expectation of a great parte, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the willes of many French men, and ſome mighty forren ennemies, GOD hath raiſed vp, and placed in the ſeate roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, him whome they reiected and proclaymed vnwearthy, I am fully and ſtedfaſtly reſolued, that he hath called and choſen him, not only to raigne ouer this realme, but alſo to be the meane of peace and vnion throughout the catho. apoſtolike and Romiſh church, and to roote out all ſchiſmes, diuiſions &amp; abuſes, that may haue bin crept in or noriſhed through the corruption of the time.
<pb facs="tcp:19600:8"/>Which foundation once laid, I will with Saint Paule adde thus much, that ſuch as do reſiſt the kings dominion ouer this realme, do reſiſt the ordinance of God, and ſo purchaſe to themſelues eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation: and therefore to the end to appeaſe Gods wrath, all the ſubiects of this crowne ought to vnite themſelues in one will, to acknowledge and obey the king, that ſo we may attaine to a peace, whereby things decayed may be redreſſed, ſmall ones increaſed, iuſtice flouriſh, and order, which by wars is ſubuerted and corrupted, be reſtored in all eſtates and ſunctions, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the king, at the humble ſuite of his good and faithfull ſubiectes may deale with the ſaide Pope, Emperour, and other Kings and Princes chriſtian, for the aſſembling and gathering of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall frée councell, wherein to aboliſh and end all controuerſies, and to reforme whatſoeuer is any where corrupted or amiſſe in matter of religion.</p>
            <p>Me thinkes that already I heare a common conſent of al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions chriſtian, to hearken to this ſo neceſſary a motion: yea, that I euen heare them ſay, that ſith the king is the dealer, and that the generall councel ſhall be aſſembled vnder his faith and word, they will not hencefoorth feare to ſend their embaſſadors and deputies, as being aſſured that euery one may come ſafely: that with all liberty they ſhall be receiued vnto a frée debating of their reaſons and declarations, and to lay open whatſoeuer the imaginations of their mindes in matter of religion, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny feare of moleſtation in their liues and perſons. For what Prince was there euer more carefull of his faith then the King? Sith his euemies haue and daily do relie thereupon, ſhal not his friends do the like? But withall it is méete that the ſaid nations togither with their embaſſadors and deputies, conſieering that it is the honor and glory of God, the quiet and ſaluation of their ſoules, and the peace and vnion of the vniuerſall Church that is to be dealt in, ſhould be admoniſhed, laying aſide all affections and particular paſſions, all couetouſnes, ambition, bitternes and obſtinacy, to come and bring to the ſaid aſſembly milde and trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table mindes, eaſie to be illuminated and guided by the light of Gods word, together with the authoritie of the doctrine of the ancient councels and fathers of the Church, and to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb facs="tcp:19600:8"/>before they enter into matter and conference, they are to méete and agrée vpon ſuch authors and bookes as they wil accept to be the arbitrators and iudges of their controuerſies.</p>
            <p>Who doubteth any longer of taking this courſe? What ſpirit of ſtrife will not lende his conſent hereto? Who is ſo great an enemy to himſelfe, and to the whole name of Chriſtianitie, as to chuſe warre and temporall weapons rather then ſpirituall? The controuerſie is ſpirituall, let it be decided with ſpiritual weapons; I am content to beléeue that we al do agrée herein, reaſon ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, neceſſitie forceth. And I hope that God who with his holy grace and prouidence guides al things, wil fauour the vows and hearty ſupplications which daily for the ſame we do and ſtill will poure forth vnto him.</p>
            <p>I haue already ſhewed that the peace of this realme muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céed of the holding of this ſaid generall councell, as alſo it will be vnpoſſible to attain to the one without the other: it ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe therefore in few words to ſay, that through peace, matter of religion muſt be ſtaied by prouiſo vntil the reſolution of what ſoeuer ſhall be agréed, decided and concluded in the ſaide generall councell. It is an vſuall courſe to knitte againe a thréede in the ſame place where it was broken: and when an Inſtrument of Muſicke is out of tune, men vſe not for to breake the reſt of the ſtrings, but by wreſting and ſlacking of them, to reduce them to a conſent and harmony as wel as they may. Euen ſo may peace be knit againe, and the harmony of this eſtate be reſtored in the place where it was broken. And this may be compaſſed by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhing things into the ſame ſtate wherein they were when the Leaguers through their manifeſt conſpiracies, commotions, and practiſes, forced the late king to reuoke the Edict that had preſerued and maintained vs ſeauen yeares on a rowe in happie peace, concord, and tranquilitie throughout the realme.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, in ſo much as the Leaguers intent in ſéeming to wiſh the king would become a catholike, is wicked and captious, as we haue already ſhewed, alſo that the intents of others that terme themſelues the kings ſeruants, and make the like wiſh, are not ſo wel grounded, but that they may be reuerſed by other as ſtrong reſons, as may appéere by ſuch as alredy haue
<pb facs="tcp:19600:9"/>beene debated, let vs hereafter ceaſe this importunate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon propoſition and principle, and henceforth inſpect all ſuch as ſhall vſe it, accompting them for ſuch, as vnder a faire and large apparance and pretence doe weare I wote not what ambitious and pernitious web, to the diſaduantage of the wealth and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the king, and the peace of his eſtate. And contrariwiſe, taking the king at his word, that he will be inſtructed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to whatſoeuer ſhall be decided and determined in a generall councell, let vs ſtand vpon this latter aduiſe, whereby procuring the kings inſtruction and conuerſion, by the ſaide ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councell we may reunite the church of God into one ſelfe religion and confeſſion of faith, which is the greateſt benefit that we can at this preſent craue of our Lord, who wil grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, in caſe our owne commodities and particular intereſtes forgotten and omitted, we ſéeke onely his honour and gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, together with the peace and vnion of all chriſtendome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19600:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
